<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.2" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="compat_guide" kind="page">
    <compoundname>compat_guide</compoundname>
    <title>Standards conformance</title>
    <tableofcontents>
      <tocsect>
        <name>X11 extensions, protocols and IPC standards</name>
        <reference>compat_guide_1compat_x11</reference>
    </tocsect>
      <tocsect>
        <name>Wayland protocols and IPC standards</name>
        <reference>compat_guide_1compat_wayland</reference>
    </tocsect>
      <tocsect>
        <name>GLX extensions</name>
        <reference>compat_guide_1compat_glx</reference>
    </tocsect>
      <tocsect>
        <name>WGL extensions</name>
        <reference>compat_guide_1compat_wgl</reference>
    </tocsect>
      <tocsect>
        <name>OpenGL on macOS</name>
        <reference>compat_guide_1compat_osx</reference>
    </tocsect>
      <tocsect>
        <name>Vulkan loader and API</name>
        <reference>compat_guide_1compat_vulkan</reference>
    </tocsect>
      <tocsect>
        <name>Vulkan WSI extensions</name>
        <reference>compat_guide_1compat_wsi</reference>
    </tocsect>
    </tableofcontents>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para>This guide describes the various API extensions used by this version of GLFW. It lists what are essentially implementation details, but which are nonetheless vital knowledge for developers intending to deploy their applications on a wide range of machines.</para>
<para>The information in this guide is not a part of GLFW API, but merely preconditions for some parts of the library to function on a given machine. Any part of this information may change in future versions of GLFW and that will not be considered a breaking API change.</para>
<sect1 id="compat_guide_1compat_x11">
<title>X11 extensions, protocols and IPC standards</title>
<para>As GLFW uses Xlib directly, without any intervening toolkit library, it has sole responsibility for interacting well with the many and varied window managers in use on Unix-like systems. In order for applications and window managers to work well together, a number of standards and conventions have been developed that regulate behavior outside the scope of the X11 API; most importantly the <ulink url="https://www.tronche.com/gui/x/icccm/">Inter-Client Communication Conventions Manual</ulink> (ICCCM) and <ulink url="https://standards.freedesktop.org/wm-spec/wm-spec-latest.html">Extended Window Manager Hints</ulink> (EWMH) standards.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>_MOTIF_WM_HINTS</computeroutput> window property to support borderless windows. If the running window manager does not support this property, the <computeroutput>GLFW_DECORATED</computeroutput> hint will have no effect.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the ICCCM <computeroutput>WM_DELETE_WINDOW</computeroutput> protocol to intercept the user attempting to close the GLFW window. If the running window manager does not support this protocol, the close callback will never be called.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the EWMH <computeroutput>_NET_WM_PING</computeroutput> protocol, allowing the window manager notify the user when the application has stopped responding, i.e. when it has ceased to process events. If the running window manager does not support this protocol, the user will not be notified if the application locks up.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the EWMH <computeroutput>_NET_WM_STATE_FULLSCREEN</computeroutput> window state to tell the window manager to make the GLFW window full screen. If the running window manager does not support this state, full screen windows may not work properly. GLFW has a fallback code path in case this state is unavailable, but every window manager behaves slightly differently in this regard.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the EWMH <computeroutput>_NET_WM_BYPASS_COMPOSITOR</computeroutput> window property to tell a compositing window manager to un-redirect full screen GLFW windows. If the running window manager uses compositing but does not support this property then additional copying may be performed for each buffer swap of full screen windows.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <ulink url="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/ClipboardManager/">clipboard manager protocol</ulink> to push a clipboard string (i.e. selection) owned by a GLFW window about to be destroyed to the clipboard manager. If there is no running clipboard manager, the clipboard string will be unavailable once the window has been destroyed.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <ulink url="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Specifications/XDND/">X drag-and-drop protocol</ulink> to provide file drop events. If the application originating the drag does not support this protocol, drag and drop will not work.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the XRandR 1.3 extension to provide multi-monitor support. If the running X server does not support this version of this extension, multi-monitor support will not function and only a single, desktop-spanning monitor will be reported.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the XRandR 1.3 and Xf86vidmode extensions to provide gamma ramp support. If the running X server does not support either or both of these extensions, gamma ramp support will not function.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the Xkb extension and detectable auto-repeat to provide keyboard input. If the running X server does not support this extension, a non-Xkb fallback path is used.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the XInput2 extension to provide raw, non-accelerated mouse motion when the cursor is disabled. If the running X server does not support this extension, regular accelerated mouse motion will be used.</para>
<para>GLFW uses both the XRender extension and the compositing manager to support transparent window framebuffers. If the running X server does not support this extension or there is no running compositing manager, the <computeroutput>GLFW_TRANSPARENT_FRAMEBUFFER</computeroutput> framebuffer hint will have no effect.</para>
<para>GLFW uses both the Xcursor extension and the freedesktop cursor conventions to provide an expanded set of standard cursor shapes. If the running X server does not support this extension or the current cursor theme does not support the conventions, the <computeroutput>GLFW_RESIZE_NWSE_CURSOR</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>GLFW_RESIZE_NESW_CURSOR</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>GLFW_NOT_ALLOWED_CURSOR</computeroutput> shapes will not be available and other shapes may use legacy images.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="compat_guide_1compat_wayland">
<title>Wayland protocols and IPC standards</title>
<para>As GLFW uses libwayland directly, without any intervening toolkit library, it has sole responsibility for interacting well with every compositor in use on Unix-like systems. Most of the features are provided by the core protocol, while cursor support is provided by the libwayland-cursor helper library, EGL integration by libwayland-egl, and keyboard handling by <ulink url="https://xkbcommon.org/">libxkbcommon</ulink>. In addition, GLFW uses some protocols from wayland-protocols to provide additional features if the compositor supports them.</para>
<para>GLFW uses xkbcommon 0.5.0 to provide compose key support. When it has been built against an older xkbcommon, the compose key will be disabled even if it has been configured in the compositor.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <ulink url="https://cgit.freedesktop.org/wayland/wayland-protocols/tree/stable/xdg-shell/xdg-shell.xml">xdg-shell protocol</ulink> to provide better window management. This protocol is part of wayland-protocols 1.12, and is mandatory for GLFW to display a window.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <ulink url="https://cgit.freedesktop.org/wayland/wayland-protocols/tree/unstable/relative-pointer/relative-pointer-unstable-v1.xml">relative pointer protocol</ulink> alongside the <ulink url="https://cgit.freedesktop.org/wayland/wayland-protocols/tree/unstable/pointer-constraints/pointer-constraints-unstable-v1.xml">pointer constraints protocol</ulink> to implement disabled cursor. These two protocols are part of wayland-protocols 1.1, and mandatory at build time. If the running compositor does not support both of these protocols, disabling the cursor will have no effect.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <ulink url="https://cgit.freedesktop.org/wayland/wayland-protocols/tree/unstable/idle-inhibit/idle-inhibit-unstable-v1.xml">idle inhibit protocol</ulink> to prohibit the screensaver from starting. This protocol is part of wayland-protocols 1.6, and mandatory at build time. If the running compositor does not support this protocol, the screensaver may start even for full screen windows.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <ulink url="https://cgit.freedesktop.org/wayland/wayland-protocols/tree/unstable/xdg-decoration/xdg-decoration-unstable-v1.xml">xdg-decoration protocol</ulink> to request decorations to be drawn around its windows. This protocol is part of wayland-protocols 1.15, and mandatory at build time. If the running compositor does not support this protocol, a very simple frame will be drawn by GLFW itself, using the <ulink url="https://cgit.freedesktop.org/wayland/wayland-protocols/tree/stable/viewporter/viewporter.xml">viewporter protocol</ulink> alongside <ulink url="https://cgit.freedesktop.org/wayland/wayland/tree/protocol/wayland.xml#n2598">subsurfaces</ulink>. This protocol is part of wayland-protocols 1.4, and mandatory at build time. If the running compositor does not support this protocol either, no decorations will be drawn around windows.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="compat_guide_1compat_glx">
<title>GLX extensions</title>
<para>The GLX API is the default API used to create OpenGL contexts on Unix-like systems using the X Window System.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the GLX 1.3 <computeroutput>GLXFBConfig</computeroutput> functions to enumerate and select framebuffer pixel formats. If GLX 1.3 is not supported, <ref refid="group__init_1gab41771f0215a2e0afb4cf1cf98082d40" kindref="member">glfwInit</ref> will fail.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>GLX_MESA_swap_control,</computeroutput> <computeroutput>GLX_EXT_swap_control</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>GLX_SGI_swap_control</computeroutput> extensions to provide vertical retrace synchronization (or <emphasis>vsync</emphasis>), in that order of preference. Where none of these extension are available, calling <ref refid="group__context_1ga12a595c06947cec4967c6e1f14210a8a" kindref="member">glfwSwapInterval</ref> will have no effect.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>GLX_ARB_multisample</computeroutput> extension to create contexts with multisampling anti-aliasing. Where this extension is unavailable, the <computeroutput>GLFW_SAMPLES</computeroutput> hint will have no effect.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>GLX_ARB_create_context</computeroutput> extension when available, even when creating OpenGL contexts of version 2.1 and below. Where this extension is unavailable, the <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_VERSION_MAJOR</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_VERSION_MINOR</computeroutput> hints will only be partially supported, the <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_DEBUG</computeroutput> hint will have no effect, and setting the <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_PROFILE</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_FORWARD_COMPAT</computeroutput> hints to <computeroutput>GLFW_TRUE</computeroutput> will cause <ref refid="group__window_1gaaccd00fafe81e2db94e8cdf55721e055" kindref="member">glfwCreateWindow</ref> to fail.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>GLX_ARB_create_context_profile</computeroutput> extension to provide support for context profiles. Where this extension is unavailable, setting the <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_PROFILE</computeroutput> hint to anything but <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_ANY_PROFILE</computeroutput>, or setting <computeroutput>GLFW_CLIENT_API</computeroutput> to anything but <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_API</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>GLFW_NO_API</computeroutput> will cause <ref refid="group__window_1gaaccd00fafe81e2db94e8cdf55721e055" kindref="member">glfwCreateWindow</ref> to fail.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>GLX_ARB_context_flush_control</computeroutput> extension to provide control over whether a context is flushed when it is released (made non-current). Where this extension is unavailable, the <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_RELEASE_BEHAVIOR</computeroutput> hint will have no effect and the context will always be flushed when released.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>GLX_ARB_framebuffer_sRGB</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>GLX_EXT_framebuffer_sRGB</computeroutput> extensions to provide support for sRGB framebuffers. Where both of these extensions are unavailable, the <computeroutput>GLFW_SRGB_CAPABLE</computeroutput> hint will have no effect.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="compat_guide_1compat_wgl">
<title>WGL extensions</title>
<para>The WGL API is used to create OpenGL contexts on Microsoft Windows and other implementations of the Win32 API, such as Wine.</para>
<para>GLFW uses either the <computeroutput>WGL_EXT_extension_string</computeroutput> or the <computeroutput>WGL_ARB_extension_string</computeroutput> extension to check for the presence of all other WGL extensions listed below. If both are available, the EXT one is preferred. If neither is available, no other extensions are used and many GLFW features related to context creation will have no effect or cause errors when used.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>WGL_EXT_swap_control</computeroutput> extension to provide vertical retrace synchronization (or <emphasis>vsync</emphasis>). Where this extension is unavailable, calling <ref refid="group__context_1ga12a595c06947cec4967c6e1f14210a8a" kindref="member">glfwSwapInterval</ref> will have no effect.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>WGL_ARB_pixel_format</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>WGL_ARB_multisample</computeroutput> extensions to create contexts with multisampling anti-aliasing. Where these extensions are unavailable, the <computeroutput>GLFW_SAMPLES</computeroutput> hint will have no effect.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>WGL_ARB_create_context</computeroutput> extension when available, even when creating OpenGL contexts of version 2.1 and below. Where this extension is unavailable, the <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_VERSION_MAJOR</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_VERSION_MINOR</computeroutput> hints will only be partially supported, the <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_DEBUG</computeroutput> hint will have no effect, and setting the <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_PROFILE</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_FORWARD_COMPAT</computeroutput> hints to <computeroutput>GLFW_TRUE</computeroutput> will cause <ref refid="group__window_1gaaccd00fafe81e2db94e8cdf55721e055" kindref="member">glfwCreateWindow</ref> to fail.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>WGL_ARB_create_context_profile</computeroutput> extension to provide support for context profiles. Where this extension is unavailable, setting the <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_PROFILE</computeroutput> hint to anything but <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_ANY_PROFILE</computeroutput> will cause <ref refid="group__window_1gaaccd00fafe81e2db94e8cdf55721e055" kindref="member">glfwCreateWindow</ref> to fail.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>WGL_ARB_context_flush_control</computeroutput> extension to provide control over whether a context is flushed when it is released (made non-current). Where this extension is unavailable, the <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_RELEASE_BEHAVIOR</computeroutput> hint will have no effect and the context will always be flushed when released.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>WGL_ARB_framebuffer_sRGB</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>WGL_EXT_framebuffer_sRGB</computeroutput> extensions to provide support for sRGB framebuffers. Where both of these extension are unavailable, the <computeroutput>GLFW_SRGB_CAPABLE</computeroutput> hint will have no effect.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="compat_guide_1compat_osx">
<title>OpenGL on macOS</title>
<para>Support for OpenGL 3.2 and above was introduced with OS X 10.7 and even then only forward-compatible, core profile contexts are supported. Support for OpenGL 4.1 was introduced with OS X 10.9, also limited to forward-compatible, core profile contexts. There is also still no mechanism for requesting debug contexts or no-error contexts. Versions of Mac OS X earlier than 10.7 support at most OpenGL version 2.1.</para>
<para>Because of this, on OS X 10.7 and later, the <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_VERSION_MAJOR</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_VERSION_MINOR</computeroutput> hints will cause <ref refid="group__window_1gaaccd00fafe81e2db94e8cdf55721e055" kindref="member">glfwCreateWindow</ref> to fail if given version 3.0 or 3.1. The <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_PROFILE</computeroutput> hint must be set to <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_CORE_PROFILE</computeroutput> when creating OpenGL 3.2 and later contexts. The <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_DEBUG</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_NO_ERROR</computeroutput> hints are ignored.</para>
<para>Also, on Mac OS X 10.6 and below, the <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_VERSION_MAJOR</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_VERSION_MINOR</computeroutput> hints will fail if given a version above 2.1, setting the <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_PROFILE</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>GLFW_OPENGL_FORWARD_COMPAT</computeroutput> hints to a non-default value will cause <ref refid="group__window_1gaaccd00fafe81e2db94e8cdf55721e055" kindref="member">glfwCreateWindow</ref> to fail and the <computeroutput>GLFW_CONTEXT_DEBUG</computeroutput> hint is ignored.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="compat_guide_1compat_vulkan">
<title>Vulkan loader and API</title>
<para>By default, GLFW uses the standard system-wide Vulkan loader to access the Vulkan API on all platforms except macOS. This is installed by both graphics drivers and Vulkan SDKs. If either the loader or at least one minimally functional ICD is missing, <ref refid="group__vulkan_1ga72e7c3757d9ff2333181a5569bb7c403" kindref="member">glfwVulkanSupported</ref> will return <computeroutput>GLFW_FALSE</computeroutput> and all other Vulkan-related functions will fail with an <ref refid="group__errors_1ga56882b290db23261cc6c053c40c2d08e" kindref="member">GLFW_API_UNAVAILABLE</ref> error.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="compat_guide_1compat_wsi">
<title>Vulkan WSI extensions</title>
<para>The Vulkan WSI extensions are used to create Vulkan surfaces for GLFW windows on all supported platforms.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>VK_KHR_surface</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>VK_KHR_win32_surface</computeroutput> extensions to create surfaces on Microsoft Windows. If any of these extensions are not available, <ref refid="group__vulkan_1gada152edc5bbbd0c2138728878632fd9c" kindref="member">glfwGetRequiredInstanceExtensions</ref> will return an empty list and window surface creation will fail.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>VK_KHR_surface</computeroutput> and either the <computeroutput>VK_MVK_macos_surface</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>VK_EXT_metal_surface</computeroutput> extensions to create surfaces on macOS. If any of these extensions are not available, <ref refid="group__vulkan_1gada152edc5bbbd0c2138728878632fd9c" kindref="member">glfwGetRequiredInstanceExtensions</ref> will return an empty list and window surface creation will fail.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>VK_KHR_surface</computeroutput> and either the <computeroutput>VK_KHR_xlib_surface</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>VK_KHR_xcb_surface</computeroutput> extensions to create surfaces on X11. If <computeroutput>VK_KHR_surface</computeroutput> or both <computeroutput>VK_KHR_xlib_surface</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>VK_KHR_xcb_surface</computeroutput> are not available, <ref refid="group__vulkan_1gada152edc5bbbd0c2138728878632fd9c" kindref="member">glfwGetRequiredInstanceExtensions</ref> will return an empty list and window surface creation will fail.</para>
<para>GLFW uses the <computeroutput>VK_KHR_surface</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>VK_KHR_wayland_surface</computeroutput> extensions to create surfaces on Wayland. If any of these extensions are not available, <ref refid="group__vulkan_1gada152edc5bbbd0c2138728878632fd9c" kindref="member">glfwGetRequiredInstanceExtensions</ref> will return an empty list and window surface creation will fail. </para>
</sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="/Users/cwb/developer/learning/graphicRenderEngine/ceres/3rdparty/glfw/docs/compat.dox"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
